Today we're here to answer one simple
question. Is this safe or not? Welcome
to bugs of C++. I don't have like an
intro animation, so let's just get on
with it. This video is pretty simple.
Could probably have just been a YouTube
short, but you know me. We're going to
dive deep. So, fundamentally, let's have
a look at this. What is actually
happening here? We have a get name
function which returns a string. It's
returning a string literal. So, it's
creating a new string. This is going to
be using the implicit constructor of
string to convert this const array into
an actual string object. We're returning
that. Here it is. And then we're doing C
string to get the underlying const
pointer buffer that is held by the
string object and we're sending that
into the print line function. Now, let
me just quickly mention that you of
course do not actually have to do this
if you're trying to print a string
because the print line function can
handle a string object. So, if anyone
here is new to C++ and you're like, why
are you doing that? That's that's not
the point of the video. The problem
here, or the potential problem here, is
that this string object, which kind of
only exists in this context here, is
responsible for holding the memory that
makes up these characters. So obviously
by that logic, since the string actually
holds the conch char buffer that makes
up the characters of the string, once
the string dies, so does the const
buffer. So if we deliberately expand
this example to what a lot of people
probably think is going on here. If I do
const pointer name equals getname dot
cring and then we try and print the
name. This tells a slightly different
story. And in fact Visual Studio is
telling me immediately that the pointer
is dangling because it points at a
temporary instance which was destroyed.
What we're doing here is we're calling
get name which returns a brand new std
string object. But notice we're not
storing it in any sort of variable. It's
sort of just transiently temporarily
existing within this line of code. So
then when we try and pull out a simple
pointer from that object and remember a
pointer is just an integer. It's just a
memory address. So it's not like it's
going to transfer ownership of that
memory or anything. No, it is literally
just a number. We're pulling an int out
of this string and storing it within
this object. So then get name which
returns our string. That string is not
being stored anywhere means that when we
go to the next line of code that string
is gone. That string has been deleted
and it has obviously freed its buffer of
memory which we are still pointing to
with our little pointer into this name
variable. So then when we go to print
that name, the print line function is
going to start reading characters from a
buffer that doesn't actually exist
anymore. It's been freed. But aren't we
doing the same thing over here? Is this
not the same code? It is the same code,
but the difference is where the actual C
string pointer is being used. In this
case, it's being passed directly into
the print line function. Think of it
this way. Get name is our string, right?
Our string dies when we hit this
semicolon at the end of our statement.
So basically what I'm saying is that
this string that we're returning, it is
safe within this exact line of code
which includes going into the print line
function. Our actual string object is
not going to die until this statement,
this expression actually finishes. When
we drop to the next line of code, it's
gone. But within this line of code, it's
still alive, which means that this is in
fact safe. The example below is a little
bit different because by our same logic
of our string existing within this line
of code, yeah, it does exist within this
line of code. And what are we doing with
it? We're simply pulling out an integer.
We're pulling out a const pointer. So
then it clearly gets destroyed after
that line of code. And when we go to
print it now with name, a pointer within
our string that has now been destroyed,
boom. Now, if you want to make sure that
you and your team catch bugs like this,
then you should check out Code Rabbit,
the sponsor of this video. Code Rabbit
is your AI co-pilot, helping you and
your team produce higher quality code.
Dev teams are moving faster than ever
with all these AI tools writing your
code for you. So, how can you possibly
keep up and ensure that you're still
delivering quality code? Code reviews
are super critical but timeconuming. So,
we need better tools to help us. Code
Rabbit is the category defining platform
for AI code reviews with contextaware
reviews that pull in dozens of points of
context. Code Rabbit provides you with
instant code review comments and shows
you the potential impact of every pull
request, meaning you can stay on top of
every change in your codebase. Code
Rabbit is a self-improving agent that
learns from all of the interactions that
you have with it with customization
features that allow you to tailor it to
your codebase. It helps organizations
catch bugs, strengthen security, and
ship reliable code at speed, which is
why it's trusted by thousands of
organizations and open-source projects
worldwide, such as Nvidia. Code Rabbit
reviews 1 million pull requests per week
across 3 million repositories and is
used by 100,000 open- source projects.
Aside from seamlessly integrating into
GitHub or GitLab, Code Rabbit is also
available in CLI and IDE. So give it a
try today and cut code review time and
bugs in half instantly. Go to
codrabbit.link/cho.
Link will be in the description below.
Huge thank you to Code Rabbit for
sponsoring this video. I think this is a
bit of a common misconception that
people have because this looks like it
might be dangerous. So, how would we
then rewrite this so that it is in fact
safe? Well, we just need to make sure
that the string is stored until we're
actually truly done with its memory. So,
instead of constame, we would just do sd
string name equals get name. And then
from there, if we really wanted it to be
like a char pointer in its own variable,
we could do something like name cring
like this. And then we would provide our
function with that. I would just rewrite
this like this though. There's no need
to pull out the constru pointer into its
own variable. But this is in fact safe.
Our string that is created by this get
name function is going to be stored
within this string variable until this
string variable name goes out of scope
which in this case is of course going to
be the end of our program. So that's it.
This is 100% safe. So either of these
are technically safe in this specific
context. However, this is kind of
guaranteed to be safe, but it's really
up to what the function is actually
doing with this pointer. For example,
this is pretty unlikely in practice, I
would have to say, but if the print line
function decided to take this conchar
pointer and store it for some reason,
and then later in the program after this
line has finished, it would then try and
use the memory at that pointer. That of
course is going to not be there anymore
because the string has been destroyed.
Now it would be pretty psychopathic for
someone to write a function like this
that takes in a pointer and then just
stores it without any kind of copying it
into its own internal buffer but just
storing the the pointer directly. Like
that doesn't really happen at least not
with a string pointer like this. But in
other cases it can certainly happen.
Like if this was a pointer to an object,
then by taking in a raw pointer into
some sort of function then and
potentially storing it, it's kind of
like a weak pointer. But again, that
would only apply if you have some sort
of external object that internally is
owning a pointer that will be freed when
that external object dies. But the point
is you don't technically know what's
happening here. Maybe some logging
library decides to buffer the log
messages and not just print them
immediately and they would just store
the conch char pointer. Again, in that
scenario, the logging library would
almost certainly copy the string into
its own internal memory so that you
wouldn't be bound by some weird lifetime
like this. Another really common example
that I see that people are unsure about
pretty often is if you have a file
system path. So, let's do get path
return image.png. If I have a file
system path and I need to get a char
pointer out of it, how do I do that? And
in fact, let's just say that I'm
actually storing this properly. So here
is my path and then I want to I don't
know display it in the UI using I'm
guey. Maybe it needs an actual char
pointer. So how do I get to a char
pointer? Well file system path does have
a cring function. However that doesn't
actually return a char. It returns a
wide string at least in MSVC's
implementation. So that's no good. I
need a normal cring. So I have to do dot
string dot cring. That is the pattern
that most people are used to. And you
can see that this can also kind of look
crazier if it's like this. So then if I
had this and I wanted to log it, would
something like this be acceptable? And
again, if we apply our rules to it, we
have a very transient string here
because path.string, this doesn't return
a const string reference or anything.
You can see it's actually constructing a
new string. And then we're calling cring
to get the pointer to the char array
buffer from within that transient
string. However, because it's all
happening within this one line and print
line will consume and be done with that
actual char pointer by the end of its
scope. This is in fact safe. I should
also note that the reason why
specifically this is unclear is because
we are constructing and returning a new
string that clearly only exists within
this line of code. If we had the
function get name return a constring
reference. So if this was actually
stored here for example and then we
simply returned the reference to this
then this of course would always work
even in that example where I was just
pulling out the string like this and
then printing it. This is legit now
because get name returns a const
reference of a string that is just
global. So it's just it's always present
and it's never going to get deleted. So
therefore this pointer will always be
valid not just within this line. The
whole point of this was that it was
constructing a new string that only
existed within the line of code that it
was used in. So you can see that things
are a little bit messy here. And that's
why I try and avoid as best as I can
writing code like this really ever. What
I normally do is I pull this out like
this. And I have path.string string and
then it's very very clear here that yes
in fact I am taking a pointer from this
string but the string is now a proper L
value it's a proper variable I've made
the lifetime super clear so even though
something like this is safe and the way
that this was written before is safe I
still prefer to write it like this now
one more thing that I want to say is the
annoying thing about this bug is that
sometimes even if you actually do things
not properly Y. So if we go back to this
example here, but I change the get name
function to use this version instead.
This clearly shouldn't work, right? I
mean, even Visual Studio says that it
shouldn't work. However, it can work.
The reason why is because at the end of
this line, the memory that this const
pointer is pointing towards has in fact
been freed, but it may not have
necessarily changed or been rewritten
yet. I mean, not much has probably
happened between these two lines of
code. And so technically if I run just
sort of this section of code then our
result is absolutely nothing is getting
printed. If I switch to a release build
and I also run this nothing again using
MSVC. However this is where it gets fun.
If we have a look at GCC same exact code
we have this being returned. We're doing
C string and then here in fact is our
conchar pointer string that we're taking
out and printing. The result is well, it
says Cherno. If we turn optimization on
and we run it again, we get a different
result. Name I don't know. But with
optimization off, name is Cherno. What
about Clang? Here's Clang. Let's run
that. We get a warning, which is nice,
but it still prints correctly. Let's try
optimization on again. Same warning, and
it didn't actually run. So maybe it
crashed. So clearly this is something
that can kind of slip through the cracks
because unless something has overwritten
that memory. Just because it's free
doesn't mean that you're completely
banned from using it. So yes, this is
something that you need to make sure
that you are careful with. And a really
good way of avoiding all of this is to
just make sure that you basically don't
have any sort of transient temporaries,
but you clearly define the scope and the
lifetime of every object whose data you
then use. and are dependent on. Hope you
all enjoyed this video. If you did,
please don't forget to hit the like
button. Let me know your thoughts in the
comment section below as well. Do you
encounter this often? How do you deal
with it? Has this ever burned you?
Because it's burned me. If you have any
other bugs that you'd like me to make a
video on, leave them in the comment
section below. And I will see you guys
next time. Goodbye.